Okay, moving on to trauma, epidural hematoma.
Epi means on top, dura refers to the dura,
and hematoma is a collection of blood.
So you get a collection of blood on top of the dura.
Now just remember, going back to normal,
here is the skull,
and remember that tightly attached to the skull is the dura.
Now this is important that it's tightly attached.
So in order to get a bleed that's going to be above the dura,
you're going to need to rupture a high-pressure circuit
so that it can separate the dura from the skull.
And so therefore, what's going to happen
is you're going to get a fracture.
This is going to rupture the middle meningeal artery,
artery because you need a high-pressure circuit,
and middle meningeal because that's the artery that runs here.
And that then is going to result in a collection of blood
between the skull and the dura.
So when you get this collection of blood,
it's going to look like this.
Here's the blood,
and of course the dura has been separated from the skull.
Now because the dura is tightly attached to the skull,
you're going to get these points at the edge of the bleed,
which are going to remain tightly attached,
and then you'll have the separation of the dura here from the skull.
And that's going to create the classic lens-shaped lesion on CT,
and you get a lens shape because it's attached here still
and still attached here.
And then what will happen over time is that blood will build up,
and as blood builds up,
the patient could be completely asymptomatic,
but all of a sudden the blood will sort of keep putting pressure on here
and eventually rupture this point or this point.
That will then further expand the hematoma,
and when you get an expansion of the hematoma,
that could then result in herniation,
which is a lethal complication.
And so this is also called the talk-and-die syndrome
because the patients can be asymptomatic for a few hours, for example,
and then all of a sudden this sort of ruptures or expands further,
and then that creates a lethal herniation.
So let's go back and read the text with that in mind.
Epidural hematoma,
you get a collection of blood between the dura and the skull,
fracture of the temporal bone with rupture of the middle meningeal artery,
particularly high yield.
You get a lens-shaped lesion on CT, particularly high yield.
You get a lucid interval that may precede the neurologic signs.
Again, you can have a few hours or even a day or so when you're totally fine,
and then all of a sudden, boom,
the hematoma expands as you sort of pull away at the dura one step further,
and then that can result in herniation,
which is a lethal complication.
Again, herniation refers to the pushing of one part of the brain
into another part of the brain, which we're going to talk about in a moment.
Subdural hematoma is when you have a collection of blood beneath the dura.
Now go back and remember that if this is the skull
and this is the dura tightly attached,
then underneath that is going to be the arachnoid,
and of course the arachnoid would then attach to the pia,
and the pia is directly connected to the brain.
And so what's going to happen here is you're going to get a bleed in this space,
and that's called a subdural hematoma underneath the dura.
Now this is usually due to rupture of a bridging vein.
The way I remember this is that you don't need a lot of pressure
to be able to rip through these little arachnoid-like spider webs,
and again arachnoid kind of also means spider,
and it usually arises with trauma.
Now remember here are these bridging veins like this,
and so these can easily rupture, especially with trauma,
resulting in a subdural hematoma.
At the same time, when there's atrophy of the brain,
these veins are going to be stretched as the brain is pulled away, for example,
and then there's increased risk of rupture with atrophy.
And so your text here says that a subdural hematoma is a collection of blood beneath the dura,
tearing of bridging veins, high yield, and it usually arises with trauma.
Here's a picture of a subdural hematoma.
This thick layer here represents the dura,
and then you can see that there's blood underneath the dura,
and it's sitting on top of the brain here.
So again, classic subdural hematoma.
This will present with progressive neurologic signs.
As the blood slowly builds up and spreads across the surface of the brain,
you'll get progressive neurologic signs,
and again herniation would be a lethal complication.
There's no space in that box for anything but the brain,
and so when you add blood, you can eventually cause a herniation.
Now again, herniation is displacement of brain tissue.
It's due to mass effect or increased intracranial pressure.
I'm going to use this simple picture to illustrate the three most common types of herniation.
The first is a tonsillar herniation.
This is relatively straightforward.
You get herniation of the cerebellar tonsils,
which is right here through the foramen magnum,
which then compresses the brainstem,
and when this compresses the brainstem,
you can get cardiopulmonary arrest.
So this first herniation is a tonsillar herniation.
The next herniation is called a subfalcine herniation.
This is when you get the cingulate gyrus, which is present here,
to herniate underneath the phalx cerebri, which is present here.
Now the problem here is that you'll compress the anterior cerebral artery,
which will then lead to infarction.
The third type of herniation is an uncoherniation.
This is when you get herniation of the uncus of the temporal lobe,
which is right here,
into the area between the cerebellum and the brainstem here,
which is also called the tentorum cerebelli.
Now the problem is that you're going to then compress three structures.
Number one, you're going to compress cranial nerve three,
and that's going to result in the eyes moving down and out with a dilated pupil.
You'll also compress the posterior cerebral artery,
which will give you infarction of the occipital lobe,
and then you can also pull on the paramedian artery that's running along the brainstem,
and that'll give you direct hemorrhages on the brainstem.
And so these are the three complications of an uncoherniation.
Moving on to demyelinating disorders,
recall that the axons of both the central and the peripheral nervous system are myelinated.
The purpose of the myelin is to improve conduction across the axons.
In the central nervous system,
the key cell that myelinates the axons is the oligodendrocyte,
and in the peripheral nervous system,
the key cell that myelinates the axons is the Schwann cell.
In a demyelinating disorder,
you get destruction of the myelin or the oligodendrocytes.
And again, here we're going to focus on the central nervous system,
so the oligodendrocytes.
In this particular case, the axons are preserved,
so you don't damage the axons,
but the conduction of the impulse across those axons is going to be impaired.
The first of these disorders is called leukodystrophies.
Leuco means white,
and dystrophy means that there's a problem within the white matter.
Of course, the white matter is white within the brain
because it's loaded with myelin,
and that's what gives it the white color.
And so leukodystrophies are inherited mutations
in enzymes necessary for the production or for the maintenance of myelin.
The first of these is metachromatic leukodystrophy.
This is when you have a deficiency of aural sulfatase.
It's the most common leukodystrophy,
and the problem here is that you can't degrade myelin.
Now recall that you produce and turn over myelin on a regular basis,
and so if you can't destroy the myelin,
that will result in a leukodystrophy.
And in this particular case, the myelin cannot be degraded,
and so it accumulates within the lysosomes.
Krabbe's disease is when you have deficiency of galactocerebroside beta-galactosidase,
and this then results in the accumulation of galactocerebroside within the macrophages.
In adrenal leukodystrophy, you have a problem with both the adrenal gland and the white matter.
This is due to impaired addition of coenzyme A to long-chain fatty acids.
The fatty acids then accumulate, damaging both the adrenal gland and the white matter.
Multiple sclerosis is autoimmune destruction of the CNS myelin and the oligodendrocytes.
Very high yield to know that it's the oligodendrocytes that are getting destroyed in multiple sclerosis.
This happens to be the most common chronic CNS disease of young adults.
Women are more commonly affected than men.
Now again, it's an autoimmune disease, and remember the general principle with autoimmune disease
is that you have a genetically susceptible individual that sees an environmental trigger.
And so the genetic susceptibility here is the association with HLA-DR2,
and the environmental trigger is that it's more commonly seen in regions away from the equator,
and that's also particularly high yield to know.
The clinical features of multiple sclerosis are dependent on the region that's involved.
So if the optic nerve is involved, you can have blurry vision in one eye.
If the brainstem is involved, the patients can have vertigo and scanning speech.
This scanning speech is particularly important in high yield,
and that's because this speech will resemble the speech of someone who's drunk,
but of course they're not drunk, they simply have multiple sclerosis.
And then involvement of the medial longitudinal fasciculus gives you something called internuclear ophthalmoplegia.
Now this is relatively high yield because it goes back to neuroanatomy,
so let's take a moment to illustrate this.
Here's the left eye and the right eye,
and of course you've got muscles coming off these eyes here.
This is the lateral rectus muscle, medial rectus.
This is the medial rectus on this side and the lateral rectus.
And what you need to know is that cranial nerve 6 directly attaches to the lateral rectus,
and so here's the nucleus of cranial nerve 6 directly attaching to the lateral rectus.
Now the medial rectus, you've got here cranial nerve 3 that sort of feeds the medial rectus,
and so this will directly feed the medial rectus on either side.
And then there'll be a crossover to the cranial nerve 6 on each side,
and what is present between this crossover is something called the medial longitudinal fasciculus here
and another medial longitudinal fasciculus here.
Now let's say that the patient wants to look to the left,
so you want to move this eye this way and this eye this way.
Well, what's going to happen is this cranial nerve 6 is going to fire,
and when it fires, it's going to drag the lateral rectus down, pulling the eye to the left,
and at the same time it's going to send a message this way,
and it's going to fire cranial nerve 3, which will drag this medial rectus down,
which will then pull the right eye to the left.
Now imagine if the medial longitudinal fasciculus is damaged,
then when you try to look to the left, you'll be able to pull the left eye to the left.
However, when you send this message up this way, it's going to be blocked because of the damage here,
and you won't be able to pull the right eye to the left.
And so this is called intranuclear ophthalmoplegia.
Additional clinical features include involvement of the cerebral white matter,
which can result in hemiparesis or unilateral loss of sensation.
The spinal cord can be involved, which would result in lower extremity loss of sensation or weakness.
And then, of course, the autonomic nervous system can be involved,
giving you bowel, bladder, and sexual dysfunction.
Now the diagnosis of multiple sclerosis is made by MRI, and it will show plaques.
You can also do a lumbar puncture, and it would show increased lymphocytes,
increased immunoglobulin with oligoclonal immunoglobulin bands.
That's high yield, oligoclonal immunoglobulin bands, and then myelin basic protein,
and that's because you've destroyed myelin, so myelin basic protein will be present in the CSF.
Here's a picture of a brain, and just remember that, of course, you've got gray matter and you've got white matter.
And the gray matter is gray because there is no myelin, and the white matter is white because there is myelin.
So when you get demyelination, what's going to happen is you're going to get gray areas within the white matter.
So, for example, this is a region here where you've got graying of the white matter,
and this represents multiple sclerosis.
The treatment of multiple sclerosis will be high-dose steroids during an acute attack,
and interferon beta can be given, which has been shown to slow the progression of the disease.
The next disorder is subacute sclerosing panencephalitis.
Encephalitis means that you've got inflammation of the brain,
and the word pan tells you that it's involving both the gray and the white matter.
This is a progressive debilitating encephalitis that leads to death,
and very high yield to know that it's due to a slowly progressing, persistent infection of the brain by measles virus.
So this is a slow, persistent infection by measles virus.
Infection actually occurs in infancy, and then the damage takes time
until eventually the neurologic signs arise years later.
It's going to be characterized by viral inclusions.
Again, this is due to measles virus within both the gray matter and the white matter.
Again, you've got a panencephalitis, and so when it's in the white matter,
that's going to be damaging the oligodendrocytes.
Progressive multifocal leukoencephalopathy is an encephalopathy that involves the white matter at multiple foci,
and it's due to JC virus infection of oligodendrocytes.
It's very high yield to note that it's JC virus infection.
Now, the patient actually has a latent JC virus infection,
but it's immunosuppression that leads to reactivation of the virus.
So, for example, AIDS can lead to reactivation of the virus.
Patients with leukemia who may be immunosuppressed, for example,
can get reactivation of the virus as well.
This presents with rapidly progressive neurologic signs that eventually lead to death.
And the final disorder is central pontine myelinolysis.
This is when you get focal demyelination of the pons, hence the word pontine,
and it occurs in the center of the pons, and it's due to rapid IV correction of hyponatremia,
particularly in an alcoholic or a patient with liver disease or someone who is severely malnourished.
And that's what I've stated here.
You get myelinolysis, which means that you start destroying the white matter within the pons.
Let's go back and remind ourselves that if this is sort of the cortex of the brain,
and then everything is coming down into a brainstem, remember that everybody is sort of feeding into this highway.
So all of the axons that are going to be running through this system are all going to come through the pons.
And so one of the consequences of central pontine myelinolysis, and particularly high yield for board exams,
is that you classically get something called locked-in syndrome.
This is when a patient's voluntary movements are completely paralyzed from head to toe.
The only exception, classically, is the eyes.
So that the only thing that the patient can move is the eyes, and that's why they call it locked-in syndrome.
It's as if the patient is locked in their own body.
And that concludes this section.